Good
morning.
Good morning. My name is Dan Margolies. I'm filling in for Rabbi
Linzer while he is otherwise occupied on vacation. Today is August 23rd,
and it is the 19th of אב. Av. Already this שבת Shabbat
is שבת מברכים, Shabbat Mevarchim, so אב Av is running out, אלול
Elul is soon, so you have to think about that. And just
before we start the גמרא, Gemara, I just want to read very
briefly from the רמב"ם Rambam in the beginning of הלכות חובל ומזיק
Hilchot Chovel U'Mazik in ספר נזיקין. Sefer Nezikin. The רמב"ם Rambam points
out the fact that, like I was saying yesterday, this is a
very polemical topic. The topic of עין תחת עין, Ayin Tachat Ayin,
how do we assess the valuation of damages in a case of
one person punches another person in the face? These are all very
important, and it sounds like at least from the פשט Pshat of
the פסוקים, Pesukim, it might mean that you actually are supposed to
injure people the way that they got that they injured others. רמב"ם
Rambam says אף על פי שדברים אלו נראים מענין תורה שבכתב, Af
Al Pi SheDevarim Elu Nir'im MeInyan Torah SheBichtav, even though the way
the הלכה Halacha comes out, that is that we require monetary restitution,
is based on דרשות Drashot and makes a certain amount of sense
based on the פסוקים, Pesukim, nonetheless כולם מפורשין הן מפי משה מהר
סיני. Kulon Mephorashin Hen MiPi Moshe MeiHar Sinai.
All of these are in the category of laws, that is the
idea that עין תחת עין Ayin Tachat Ayin means monetary restitution is
in the category of תורה שבעל פה Torah SheBa'al Peh of דברים
המקובלים מפי משה רבינו, Devarim HaMekubalim MiPi Moshe Rabbeinu,
things that were transmitted orally to משה Moshe and were transmitted through
all the generations. And רמב"ם Rambam continues, all of these are הלכה
למעשה הן בידינו, Halacha Lema'aseh Hen B'Yadeinu, this is how our courts
act, אלו אבותינו דנים בבית דינו של יהושע בית דינו של שמואל
הרמתי וכל בית דין ובית דין שעמדו מימות משה ועד עכשיו. Elu
Avoteinu Danim BeBeit Dino Shel Yehoshua, Beit Dino Shel Shmuel HaRamati VeChol
Beit Din VeBeit Din She'Amdu Mi'Mot Moshe Ve'Ad Achshav.
Every בית דין Beit Din in Jewish history from the time of
יהושע, Yehoshua, from the time of שמואל, Shmuel, has always understood עין
תחת עין Ayin Tachat Ayin to mean monetary compensation. And that's because
that's the tradition going back. The reason why there are all of
these דרשות Drashot is because the category of דברים המקובלים מפי משה
רבינו Devarim HaMekubalim MiPi Moshe Rabbeinu are things which might have a
certain hint in the תורה Torah text or make a certain amount
of logical sense. It's a separate category from הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha
LeMoshe MiSinai. הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai are things which have
no connection to the text at all, which are totally based on
tradition. So that's a difference between this category and those. So where
was that רמב"ם? Rambam? That's the רמב"ם Rambam right in the first
chapter of הלכות חובל ומזיק. Hilchot Chovel U'Mazik. And we are going
to pick up where we left off yesterday on the fourth from
the bottom line on פ"ג ע"ב Pei Gimmel Amud Bet where it
says תניא. Tanya.
I'm sorry, the גמרא Gemara didn't use that לשון Lashon of דברים
המקובלים מפי משה רבינו? Devarim HaMekubalim MiPi Moshe Rabbeinu?
Correct.
That's the רמב"ם's Rambam term. According to the רמב"ם, Rambam, there are
five categories of תורה שבעל פה. Torah SheBa'al Peh. Number one are
דברים המקובלים מפי משה רבינו, Devarim HaMekubalim MiPi Moshe Rabbeinu, things which
are received tradition but which do have a certain hint in the
text and about which there's no מחלוקת. Machloket. That's category number one.
Is that an אסמכתא?
Asmachta? Is that an אסמכתא?
Asmachta? So if there are דרשות, Drashot, to a certain extent it's
coming up with the דרשה Drasha afterwards for a הלכה Halacha that
we already know. Okay. Number two is הלכה למשה מסיני. Halacha LeMoshe
MiSinai. הלכה למשה מסיני Halacha LeMoshe MiSinai has no hint in the
text, but also has no מחלוקת, Machloket, and that's also a tradition
going back. The third category about which all of the מחלוקות Machlokot
are about is the question of things learned out from דרשות. Drashot.
According to the רמב"ם, Rambam, things that are learned out from דרשות,
Drashot, because there's a certain amount of discretion in making those דרשות,
Drashot, so that's where the מחלוקת Machloket comes from. And the last
two categories are גזירות Gezeirot and תקנות. Takanot. What's the difference between
a גזירה Gezeira and a תקנה Takana is for another time. So
the גמרא Gemara says, picking up from the fourth from the bottom
line on פ"ג ע"ב Pei Gimmel Amud Bet in בבא קמא. Bava
Kamma. We started פרק החובל Perek HaChovel yesterday. The משנה Mishna had
listed five different things that you have to pay, different types of
compensation, and the גמרא Gemara had launched us into a discussion of
how do we know that there's monetary compensation at all? Doesn't עין
תחת עין Ayin Tachat Ayin sound like if somebody blinds somebody's eye,
you poke out their eye? So we saw the first main attempt
yesterday, which was the discussion of well maybe it's learned out from
a גזירה שוה Gezeira Shava from מכה מכה, Makeh Makeh, learned from
when
if a person injures an animal, מכה בהמה ישלמנה, Makeh Beheima Yeshalmena,
that if you injure an animal, you have to pay back the
damage caused. We're going to see many other attempts today. The first
part of today's דף Daf is going to be a discussion of
many other attempted proofs for why עין תחת עין Ayin Tachat Ayin
refers to monetary compensation.
But clearly they were uncomfortable with...
Well clearly they were exactly, that's exactly the point, which is to
say in trying to defend what was fundamentally an oral tradition against
its critics, you have to be able to provide some kind of
justification,
particularly in a society where other cultures had followed a law that
took it literally, it became important for חז"ל Chazal to justify, and
that again we see in the Middle Ages as well. אבן עזרא
Ibn Ezra quotes from סעדיה גאון Saadia Gaon many polemics against the
Karaites about this, and the רמב"ם's Rambam point is clearly a polemical
point in הלכות חובל ומזיק. Hilchot Chovel U'Mazik. We have to clarify,
you know, this really
always...
חזל Chazal cared about פשט. pshat.
Well, חזל Chazal always cared about פשט. pshat. But this isn't exactly
about פשט. pshat. It's about can we make דרשות drashot that justify
what in the end boils down to boils down to tradition. So
let's see what it says here. תניא. Tanya. רבי דוסתאי בן יהודה
אומר: Rabbi Dostai ben Yehuda omer: עין תחת עין, ayin tachat ayin,
ממון אתה אומר mamon ata omer ממון mamon או אינו אלא עין
ממש? o eino ela ayin mamash? So how do we know it
refers to money and not just a real eye, that is you
poke somebody's eye out? So אמר הרי שהיה עינו של זה גדולה
ועינו של זה קטנה. amar hare shehaya eino shel ze gedola ve-eino
shel ze ktana. So if one person, that is the person who
injured, the מזיק, mazik, had a big eye and the ניזק, nizak,
the one who was damaged, had a very small eye. Ah, okay,
so that's a question. What does the size have to do with
this? So some interpretations might say, so some of the מפרשים mefarshim
might say size doesn't really mean size, like the physical size doesn't
obviously matter that much, but it's about the quality of vision. What
if the person who was the מזיק mazik had very good sight?
They should have said that.
They should have said that. So that's not what it says. So
small and large is a good question. What does that have to
do with it? Perhaps also just means if you're going to injure
one third of his eye, well that'll be a larger piece than
if you injured one third, if he injured one third of your
eye.
Could it have at least some sort of semblance of sense to
it?
Okay, so we're going to take it to the point where the
idea of fully reciprocal punishment is going to become nonsensical
because there's no case in which it's going to be perfectly equal.
So that's exactly the point. עינו של זה גדולה ועינו של זה
קטנה. eino shel ze gedola ve-eino shel ze ktana. היכי אני קורא
בה heich ani kore ba עין תחת עין? ayin tachat ayin? It
can't be one eye in place of the other because they're not
equal. Okay, וכי תימא כל כי האי שקיל מיניה ממונא. vechi teima
kol ki hai shakil minei mamona. So התורה אמרה HaTorah amra משפט
אחד יהיה לכם. mishpat echad yihye lachem. So if you take money,
then that's fine. So the תורה Torah requires that you say משפט
אחד יהיה לכם. mishpat echad yihye lachem. That the valuation or the
assessment in a just system should be equivalent in every case, that
is there has to be a way of doing it equally. משפט
השווה לכולכם, mishpat hashave lekulchem, the law has to be the same
for everyone. So if one person has a large eye and one
person has a small eye, then the law will be unfair because
it would require either blinding one person's very large eye, which would
be a larger loss, or vice versa. Okay, so that makes sense.
Okay, I hear that, that critique certainly is a good question, which
is that the physical size doesn't seem as relevant to the question
as anything else. Okay, so אמרי מאי קושיא דילמא נהורא שקיל מיניה
נהורא אמר רחמנא נשקול מיניה. amrei mai kushya dilma nehora shakil minei
nehora amar Rachmana nishkol minei. So maybe it's just referring to the
fact that since he took away vision that you take away his
vision and it doesn't actually have to do with the physical eye,
so who cares about the size of the eye? So אמר רחמנא
נשקול מיניה. amar Rachmana nishkol minei. דאילו de-ilu so that then in
that case you could blind his eye because if it was something
fully equivalent then you could. So לא תימא הכי קטן שהרג את
הגדול בגדול שהרג את הקטן, lo teima hachi katan she-harag et hagadol
begadol she-harag et hakatan, היכי קטלינן ליה? heichi katlinan lei? התורה אמר
HaTorah amar משפט אחד יהיה לכם, mishpat echad yihye lachem, משפט השווה
לכולכם. mishpat hashave lekulchem. So the rejoinder is, well what if a
short person killed a very tall person? And we know that's a
capital crime. So but oh, it's a large person and a small
person, so then in that case it wouldn't be equivalent, the life
lost compared to the life that the capital punishment will be taking
won't be equivalent. And the law has to be fair and equal,
so that why can't you say that? Okay, אלא נשמה שקיל מיניה
נשמה אמר רחמנא נשקול מיניה. ela neshama shakil minei neshama amar Rachmana
nishkol minei. So in that case the reason why we say does
count as equivalent is because one life is equivalent more or less
to another life. If the תורה Torah said take his life, and
then that's what you do, and that's equivalent. One life is equivalent
to another life, so הכא נמי נהורא שקיל מיניה נהורא אמר רחמנא
נשקול מיניה. hacha nami nehora shakil minei nehora amar Rachmana nishkol minei.
So if he took away a person's sight, then you should take
away his sight, and that should be considered equivalent enough. So that's
a rejection of רבי... Rabbi... רבי דוסתאי בן יהודה's Rabbi Dostai ben
Yehuda suggestion. That is we're going to see many דרשות drashot here
that are going to have a suggestion, and many of them will
be rejected. So that was a rejection of רבי דוסתאי בן יהודה
Rabbi Dostai ben Yehuda because his idea of the equivalence kind of
doesn't hold water when compared to capital case. The capital case we
basically say every life is more or less equivalent in court, so
every eye should be considered more or less equivalent in court as
well.
So but we still convert to what we said yesterday, that is
עין תחת עין, ayin tachat ayin, that's a I mean מכה נפש
בהמה makeh nefesh behema and whatever.
That that one seemed to be well fleshed out and well supported,
but we're going to see it's a מחלוקת תנאים, machloket tanaim, so
there and אמוראים, amoraim, so they're going to be many other approaches.
So we have to go through all of them.
Okay, taking a life here seems to be equivalent to the taking
of vision as opposed to
but vision of the right, it's not the physical eye. Right. עינא
אמר רחמנא? eina amar Rachmana? No. It says נהורא אמר רחמנא. nehora
amar Rachmana. Right.
Right. So as of this moment is the תלמוד Talmud considering the
possibility that I could blind somebody? It's not the issue of the
size of the eye, but the absence of the absence of sight,
exactly.
It's more spiritual or intangible. And the other thing to note, of
course, important point, well, it's going to come up later as well,
but
the—fine, leave that for now. Okay. Okay. תני אידך. Tani Idach. So,
another suggestion. רבי שמעון בן יוחי אומר, Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai omer,
עין תחת עין, ayin tachat ayin, ממון אתה אומר ממונו אינו אלא
עין ממש. mamon ata omer mamono eino ela ayin mamash. So that's
the same question. Is it a real eye or is it money?
Okay. שהרי שיסומא, sheharei shesumma, what if a person was blind himself,
וסימי, v'simmei, and then he went and blinded someone else? So now
there's no way he could be reciprocated because he already can't see.
So there's no way you could take away his sight. Or
קיטייא וקיטייא, kiteia v'kiteia, or if he had his limb amputated and
then he amputated someone else's limb.
חיגר בחיגר.
chigger b'chigger. What is קיטייא kiteia and חיגר? chigger?
קיטייא kiteia as far as I understand is missing a limb and
חיגר chigger is limping, unable to walk. Okay. דהיכא אני מקיים בזה
עין תחת עין? d'heicha ani mekayem b'zeh ayin tachat ayin? So in
those cases, since the reciprocity would be impossible, the person already has
the injury which he has now caused to someone else, so there's
no chance for reciprocity, you could not say עין תחת עין. ayin
tachat ayin. והתורה אמרה משפט אחד יהיה לכם משפט השוה לכולכם. vehaTorah
amra mishpat echad yihiyeh lachem mishpat hashaweh lekulchem. And the principle has
to apply equally to all cases. Therefore we can't
say—wait.
Why would you think it means that?
First of all—that's a דרשא drasha though. It's not the פשט. pshat.
What doesn't make sense?
First of all, it's not משפט אחד, mishpat echad, it's
for you and the
גר. ger. That's the פסוק. pasuk.
Okay, so and how often does הלכה halacha always only care about
what it means in context in the פסוק?
pasuk? But if you're going to קוועטש kvetch it, then you can
go—real answer.
But this is their answer. Their principle is משפט אחד יהיה לכם
mishpat echad yihiyeh lachem is a real defining principle in הלכה halacha
that is you can't tell me a person who is blind we're
going to make him pay money, person who's not blind we're going
to poke out his eye. They don't—that's what they're saying doesn't make
sense. You might not like it, but that's what they're saying. I
don't like it. Okay, you can not like it. You're allowed. It's
still הלכה. halacha. Okay.
So משפט השוה לכולכם. mishpat hashaweh lekulchem. אמרי ומאי קשיא דילמא היכא
דאפשר אפשר היכא דלא אפשר לא אפשר. amri u'mai kashya dilma heicha
d'efshar efshar heicha d'lo efshar lo efshar. So maybe you should just
say, "Oh, in cases where it's possible, then you do it." That
is a seeing person who blinds another person, you would blind that
person. And if a blind person blinded someone, then you would just
require compensation.
Right. So then what happened to a second ago משפט אחד השוה
לכולכם? mishpat echad hashaweh lekulchem?
So that's the question. This is שקלא וטריא. shakla v'tarya. You ask
a question, you give an answer.
It doesn't sound like either.
Okay, so your
question, okay. ומאי קשיא דילמא היכא דאפשר אפשר היכא דלא אפשר לא
אפשר ופטרינן ליה האי
לא תימא הכי
דאילו תימא הכי.
u'mai kashya dilma heicha d'efshar efshar heicha d'lo efshar lo efshar upatrinan
lei hai lo tema hachi
d'ilu tema hachi.
So right, okay. So טריפה שהרג את השלם, treifa sheharag et hashalem,
what if a person who was—was mortally wounded, that is, is going
to die within a few months, let's say, killed someone who was
healthy? Okay. מאי עבדינן ליה? mai avdinan lei? What would you do
in that case? Because in such a case similarly, if you look
in רש"י, Rashi, you see what רש"י Rashi says. מאי עבדינן ליה?
mai avdinan lei? The last wide line in the top on רש"י.
Rashi. הא גברא קטילא הוא. ha gavra katila hu. A טריפה, treifa,
a person who has this mortal injury is going to die eventually
relatively soon. We have a presumption that this person is already halachically
considered quote unquote a dead person already, גברא קטילא, gavra katila, that
is, to a certain extent, their life is already over. And therefore,
if they would be executed at that point, then it wouldn't be
equivalent to having killed a healthy person. If you kill a healthy
person, you've taken away years and years and years of their life.
If you kill a טריפה, treifa, you've taken away a month or
two of their life. So that's רש"י's Rashi point. And therefore והוה
ליה עדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה. vehavalei edut she'i ata yakhol lehazimah.
And therefore, and this becomes a problem, רבי עקיבא איגר Rabbi Akiva
Eiger has a question on it, is according to רש"י, Rashi, this
case then, if a טריפה, treifa, a person with a mortal injury,
killed a healthy person, and then the witnesses came and said—testified that
that person killed this person, they're trying to get him executed by
death penalty. That's עדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה. edut she'i ata yakhol
lehazimah. That's like we saw a few days ago, it's a set
of witnesses who can't be considered conspiring witnesses, they can't be turned
into עדים זוממים. edim zomemim. Why? Because there's no possibility for that,
דהאי משתכחי עדים זוממים פטורים דגברא קטילא בעו למקטל. dahai mishtakchei edim
zomemim peturim d'gavra katila ba'ei l'miktal.
Because if they will then be proven to be עדים זוממים, edim
zomemim, if they'll be proven to have been conspiring witnesses, well, all
they were trying to do, says רש"י, Rashi, is to kill a
גברא קטילא, gavra katila, to kill a person who's already as if
considered dead. And therefore, we wouldn't execute them. And that would be
עדות שאי אתה יכול להזימה. edut she'i ata yakhol lehazimah. And one
of the disqualifications of witnesses is we don't accept any testimony that
does not retain the protections of the system of עדים זוממים. edim
zomemim. That is, to be a good witness, it has to have
the potential to turn into conspiring witnesses. That's a safeguard of the
legal system.
Nevertheless, this—this would apply to someone who's already been sentenced to death
and between
the sentence— Right, and that's discussed
in the first פרק perek in מסכת, masechet, first פרק, perek, third
פרק? perek? Oh, now I'm not remembering. I think it's the first
פרק perek in מסכת ערכין Masechet Arachin discusses what about a person
who is already יוצא להריג, yotze leharyeg, a person whose court case
had already been finalized, he's walking on death row, walking,
dead man walking on the green mile. Right, so he's walking down,
walking down to the electric chair, as it will not the electric,
to the סקילה skilah cliff. He's going to the סקילה skilah cliff.
So at that point if a person says, oh, ערכי עלי, erki
alai, I would have to pay my ערך erech to the בית
המקדש, Beis Hamikdash, we say, היוצא להריג לא נערך ולא מעריכין אותו.
hayotze leharyeg lo nerach velo maarichin oso. So other people can't consider
his value for ערכין arachin and he even himself can't assess his
value for ערכין, arachin, so he's considered as if he's already dead
in that case.
Yeah, but unless he tried to do it so a גוסס goses
would be killed.
Okay, and we have a whole discussion about what's the difference between
a טריפה treifah and a גוסס goses and how, and
yes,
those are extensive and obviously הלכה למעשה halacha l'maaseh in terms of
medical questions nowadays, so-called pulling the plug situations are very complicated and
qualified פוסקים poskim should be consulted and medical experts, etc., etc., etc.
Okay, so okay, אלא היכי דאפשר אפשר היכי דלא אפשר לא אפשר
ופטרינן ליה. ella heichi d'efshar efshar heichi delo efshar lo efshar upatrinan
lei. So then we have now an answer for Rabbi Shimon Bar
Yochai, exactly Michael's objection, which is, okay, so then if it's possible
to reciprocate punishment, then you should do that. And if it's not
possible, then you have another possibility. Either he's פטור patur or perhaps
you פטרינן ליה patrinan lei him from the physical injury but you
would allow him to pay monetary compensation.
פטרינן ליה patrinan lei here means you don't kill him but he
has to pay?
I'm not sure. You could read it either way. פטרינן ליה patrinan
lei could mean פטור patur from the physical injury, therefore you have
to pay, that you're פטור patur from the ideal case. Or maybe
it just means totally פטור. patur. So but that's why this suggestion
is seems to be rejected. So דבי רבי ישמאל תנא אמר קרא.
d'bei Rabi Yishmael tana amar kra. So a now this is our
what, fourth suggestion today. So the תנא tana from Rabbi Yishmael's school
says, אמר קרא כי ינתן בו. amar kra ki yinaten bo. So
this is referring to, right, כאשר יתן מום באדם כן ינתן בו,
kaasher yitein mum ba'adam ken yinaten bo, that whatever you do to
someone else should be done to you. It's a different part of
the paragraph that discusses עין תחת עין. ayin tachat ayin. He says,
אין נתינה אלא ממון. ein netinah ella mammon. ינתן בו yinaten bo
will be given, not given to him the injury will be given
to him, but he will have to pay the money compensating for
that injury. אין נתינה אלא ממון, ein netinah ella mammon, that is
the word נותן noten doesn't refer to giving an injury, the word
נותן noten refers to giving money.
What do you do with כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו? kaasher asa
ken yeaseh lo?
Okay, so talk to תנא דבי רבי ישמאל. tana d'bei Rabi Yishmael.
Okay, that's his דרשה. drasha. He says, כן ינתן בו, ken yinaten
bo, ינתן yinaten means you pay money. אלא מעתה כאשר יתן מום
באדם? ella ma'ata kaasher yitein mum ba'adam? So what do you mean?
We see the word נותן noten is used to refer to an
injury as well, giving someone an injury.
הכי נמי דממון הוא. hach nami de mammon hu. So in that
case you would also say that that refers to monetary injury, obviously
not because it says a מום, mum, a מום mum is a
physical injury. דאמרי דבי רבי ישמאל קרא יתירה דרשי. deamri d'bei Rabi
Yishmael kra yateira darshei. So maybe we can say that the תנא
דבי רבי ישמאל, tana d'bei Rabi Yishmael, if we remember Rabbi Yishmael
is more restrictive about which types of דרשות drashot he's willing to
make, so perhaps he's only willing to make this דרשה drasha because
the word כן ינתן בו ken yinaten bo is an extra word.
That is, he's not telling you the word נתינה netinah means always
means financial compensation rather than giving the injury. He means in that
פסוק pasuk the word כי ינתן בו, ki yinaten bo, that ינתן
yinaten is extra and he's willing to make a דרשה drasha from
an extra word.
מכדי ואיש כי יתן מום בעמיתו כאשר עשה כן יעשה לו. michti
ve'ish ki yitein mum ba'amito kaasher asa ken yeaseh lo. So the
another פסוק, pasuk, a person who gives an injury to his friend,
so whatever he did should be done back to him. כי ינתן
בו למה לי? ki yinaten bo lama li? So then it's redundant.
So why does it say כי ינתן בו? ki yinaten bo? שמע
מינה ממון. shma mina mammon. כן ינתן בו
למה לי שמע מינה ממון. ken yinaten bo lama li shma mina
mammon. So that's Rabbi Yishmael, the תנא דבי רבי ישמאל's tana d'bei
Rabi Yishmael opinion. כאשר יתן מום באדם למה לי? kaasher yitein mum
ba'adam lama li? So then why does it say that he gave
an injury to his friend? That also seems redundant based on these
other פסוקים. pesukim. למה לי אידי דבעי למכתב כי כן ינתן בו
כתב נמי כאשר יתן מום באדם. lama li idi debae lemichtav ki
ken yinaten bo katav nami kaasher yitein mum ba'adam. So no, then
he used a parallel formulation. Since it said כי ינתן בו ki
yinaten bo to refer to the financial compensation, it said כאשר יתן
מום באדם kaasher yitein mum ba'adam to make clear that financial compensation
becomes equivalent in the eyes of הלכה halacha going back to the
initial injury. Okay, now another suggestion. רבי חייא תנא אמר קרא. Rabi
Chiya tana amar kra. So a תנא tana from the school of
Rabbi Chiya
said, that's not rejected.
That doesn't seem to be rejected. That actually, right, תנא דבי רבי
ישמאל's tana d'bei Rabi Yishmael position seems to be a reasonable position.
We didn't have any good קושיות kashas on it. So at least
for now
but because it's יתיר yateir basically.
Right,
he has an extra word, he made a דרשה drasha on the
extra word to say that that's financial compensation. And again the question
is if we're going to have a few, a few different דרשות
drashot at the end, is there any, what's the נפקא מינה nafka
mina between any of them? Like they're all here to support the
same. Each of those is really talking about ממון. mamon. So as
we have to
see. So רבי
חייא תנא אמר קרא. Rebbe Chiya tana amar kra.
Somehow we don't do the same thing with אצבעא של גדי. Otzeva
shel Gdi.
Okay, so they do something else with אצבעא של גדי. Otzeva shel
Gdi. They have an extended סוגיא sugya about that too. Okay, so
we'll get there in a few months.
It's hard to digest. No pun intended, right?
So דבי
רבי חייא תנא אמר קרא.
Debei Rebbe Chiya tana
amar kra. יד ביד. Yad beyad. So one of the equivalences is,
you know, each of these injuries, one of them the פסוק pasuk
says יד ביד, yad beyad, a hand for a hand. But a
hand for a hand doesn't mean hand for hand, that is if
you cut someone's hand off, you're going to have your hand cut
off. Rather it means דבר הניתן מיד ליד. dabar ha-nitan mi-yad le-yad.
It means what is given from hand to hand, that is money.
That is you pay back the value of the hand. ומאי ניהו?
U-mai nihu? ממון. Mamon. אלא מעתה, Ella me'ata, רגל ברגל? regel beregel?
So but then why does the פסוק pasuk also have to say
a foot for a foot or leg for a leg depending? So
נמי הכי הוא אמרי nami hachi hu amri דבי רבי חייא Debei
Rebbe Chiya קרא יתירה קדרשי. kra yatera kadarshi. So no, the fact
is that רבי חייא, Rebbe Chiya, the תנא tanna of רבי חייא'ס
Rebbe Chiya's school is also only דרש-ing darshan the fact that there's
an extra word, that is there's a redundant phrase. So מכדי כתיב
michdi chtiv ועשיתם
לו כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו, va'asitem lo ka'asher zamam la'asot le'achiv, by
conspiring witnesses, עדים זוממים edim zomemim we say, we do to them
what they tried to do to their friend, that is they conspired
against this person and said wanted to get him to pay a
hundred dollars, so they're going to have to pay a hundred dollars.
They wanted to kill him then they're going to be killed. If
they wanted to
say that this כהן Kohen is really a בן גרושה, Ben Grusha,
the first משנה mishna in מכות, Makkot, well then we give them
forty lashes because we don't have any equivalent punishment to give them.
Okay. ועשיתם לו כאשר זמם לעשות לאחיו Va'asitem lo ka'asher zamam la'asot
le'achiv אי סלקא דעתך ממש Ei salka dach-tach mamash יד ביד? yad
beyad? So ממש mamash יד ביד yad beyad למה לי? lama li?
So if we would say that by עדים זוממים, edim zomemim, conspiring
witnesses, we would give them a full reciprocal punishment, punishment punishment, that
is we actually if they wanted to I can't even really think
about it but that their hand would be cut, if they wanted
to get this guy's hand cut off so we should cut their
hands cut off, that is כאשר עשיתם לעשות לאחיו ka'asher asitem la'asot
le'achiv that they wanted to actually do to him, if you think
that that's ממש, mamash so יד ביד yad beyad למה לי? lama
li? Then why do we have to say יד ביד? yad beyad?
So משמע מינה mashma mina ממון. mamon. So רגל ברגל regel beregel
למה לי? lama li? So then why do I have רגל ברגל
regel beregel which is again redundant? So אדי דכתיב adi d'chtiv יד
ביד yad beyad כתב נמי katav nami רגל ברגל. regel beregel. So
it sounds redundant because why do you have יד ביד yad beyad
and רגל ברגל? regel beregel? Okay.
So that seems to be the answer, the fact that there's that
redundancy comes to teach the ממון. mamon.
Wait wait, so I have a question. Yeah. So are we saying
here concluding that they would only have to pay monetary damages?
That's the thrust of the entire דף daf and a half, the
whole סוגיא.
sugya. In this particular?
Yeah for sure.
Right. So is that how we hold?
So by עדים זוממים edim zomemim exactly well by capital crime, if
they wanted to accuse someone of a capital crime then they're executed.
But if they try to accuse someone of a monetary crime or
or monetary obligation?
You're using the argument
to prove the
argument because the original person we're trying to decide if the original
person would be receiving a...
Oh you're saying it's a circular argument. Yeah, it seems a little
bit circular.
Not circular, I don't see it as circular. I saw it as
עדים זוממים edim zomemim the law is clear, here the law is
not clear. The primary thing is not clear. Is it monetary or
is it literal? But we know, we know that the law for
עדים זוממים edim zomemim in a case of damages is always going
to be money. So if that's going to be money so then
the original...
But that's circular.
That's assuming that עדים זוממים edim zomemim is money and not if
they wanted to cut his hand off that they'll have their hand
cut off.
No I'm assuming, apparently that was like known, that was like clearly
established.
Or perhaps it's clearly established
the punishment on the original person that the עדים edim are coming
to contradict. Right, if we're saying that he's never going to get
his hand cut off but only...
Right then how come the עדים edim right will have to pay
money so it must
be exactly right whether to cut their hand off or not.
That is the well that's exactly the point, that is they're trying
to make him do X. And we know that when they fail
and are proven guilty they should get X. Problem is we know
that all they have to do is pay money. Therefore it must
be that the thing that he would have had to do is
also only pay money. Right.
נפקא מינא, Nafka mina, right, what was...
And then it's redundant because we have יד ליד, yad leyad, therefore
we can go back and say יד ליד yad leyad must mean
in a normal case of compensation also only means... It is a
little bit circular.
But the point is if they wanted to have him killed they
would be killed, we don't pay money.
For sure, right, because that's כאשר זמם לעשות
לאחיו.
ka'asher zamam
la'asot le'achiv.
Right, so you're you're splitting your vote. If it's capital then we
do say that but if it's not then we don't.
Oh so we'll get to it when we get to מסכת מכות.
Masechet Makkot. But yes. Okay, it's a long דף, daf, we have
to keep going. Okay, so the next suggestion. אביי אמר. Abaye omer.
So now we get into אמוראים Amoraim interestingly enough. So אביי Abaye
says, so אתיא דתנא דבי חזקיה. azya d'tana de'bei Chizkiya. אביי'ס Abaye's
quoting from the school of חזקיה. Chizkiya. אביי אומר. Abaye omer. So
now we get into אמוראים Amoraim interestingly enough. So אביי Abaye says,
so אתיא מדתני דבי חזקיה. asya mi-detanya de-vei Chizkiyah. אביי Abaye is
quoting from the school of חזקיה Chizkiyah from a תנא דבי חזקיה,
tanna de-vei Chizkiyah, עין תחת עין נפש תחת נפש. Ayin tachas ayin
nefesh tachas nafesh. So you pay eye for an eye and a
life for a life. Important to note in biblical Hebrew the word
נפש nefesh probably actually just means the throat. That's where the breath
is. So it comes to mean the life of a person and
a self and the soul and all other sorts of things because
it goes back to that idea of the throat. עין תחת עין
נפש תחת נפש Ayin tachas ayin nefesh tachas nafesh ולא נפש ועין
תחת עין ve-lo nefesh va-ayin tachas ayin and you cannot take a
person's life and take their eye for taking out an eye. דאי
סלקא דעתך ממש, Di salka dach-tach mamash, if you'd say it actually
means you poke out his eye, זימנין דמשכחת לה עין ונפש תחת
עין zimnin di-mash-kachat lah ayin ve-nefesh tachas ayin דבהדי דעויר ליה נפקא
ליה נשמתיה. de-bahadi de-avir leh nafka leh nishmateh. There are sometimes that
undergoing that kind of a procedure, that is poking someone's eye out,
could actually kill the person, either from the pain or from the
bleeding, especially if they could get an infection, things like that. So
there are times where to try to take someone's vision away would
end up killing them. And that would be
totally unsupported by the text, that would go against the פשט. pshat.
ומאי קושיא דילמא
אומדנא אומדינן ליה? u-mai kushya dilma omdana omdinan leh? So maybe we
have to assess the person beforehand how much they'll be able to
take and we can't do it to them if we think that
they might die from this. אי מצי לקבולי עבדינן ליה, ei matzi
le-kabulei avdinan leh, if they are able then we would do it
to them. ואי לא מצי לקבולי לא עבדינן ליה, ve-ei lo matzi
le-kabulei lo avdinan leh, if they find that they won't be able
to take it then we won't do it to them. ואי אומדנא
דמצי לקבולי ועבדינן ביה ונפקא רוחיה? ve-ei omdana de-matzi le-kabulei va-avdinan beh
ve-nafka rucheh? And what if while you're assessing him to see whether
he'll be able to take it, even with that then he's going
to die from that? ובמאי לימות? u-ve-mai lamot? So מיתה לאו תנא
הוא גבי מלקות? misa lav tanna hu gabi malkus? Yeah.
Okay,
but the point is that that's unfair.
You're not allowed to, the גמרא's Gemara answer right.
Meaning, we
do, like תנן גבי מלקות. tenan gabi malkus. Right.
We try our best, right. We try our best to see what
we can find out. So he says תנן גבי מלקות אומדוהו ומת
תחת ידו פטור. tenan gabi malkus amduhu va-met tachas yado patur. So
if in trying to assess how many lashes a person could take,
the בית דין Beis Din because a בית דין Beis Din is
only allowed to hit you up until to not lash you to
death because it's not a capital crime that you're getting lashes for.
So therefore, if they were assessing how many lashes a person could
take and then
מת תחת ידו פטור met tachas yado patur then the representative of
the בית דין Beis Din who's giving the lashes is exempt from
that. Okay. רב זביד משמיה דרבא אמר אמר קרא פצע תחת פצע.
Rav Zvid mishmeih de-Rava amar amar kera petza tachas patza. He has
a different explanation. פצע תחת פצע, Petza tachas patza, a burn for
a burn. ליתן צער במקום נזק. Liten tza'ar bi-makom nezek. It refers
to a burn, which is a very painful injury, to suggest the
fact that צער tza'ar that is a payment for pain and suffering
is paid equivalent to the way that נזק nezek is paid. That
is צער, tza'ar, obviously you don't cause someone pain, you have to
pay them back for pain and suffering. So too you pay the
נזק nezek as well, which is money.
Why do you say פצע petza is a
burn, כוויה kvayah is a burn?
So פצע petza is what, a bruise, a
wound? A wound, an open wound. Fine, okay. But more or less
the same, that is a painful injury. It has צער. tza'ar. Okay.
אי סלקא דעתך isalka daitach ממש mamash, and if you think it
actually means to injure this person, כי היכי דלהוי ליה צערא. ki
heichi de-lehavei leh tza'ara. So then why do you need to have
this הלכה, halacha, צער במקום נזק, tza'ar bi-makom nezek, that you pay
back the pain and suffering? He's already going to have experienced the
pain himself because he's going to have received the injury. That is,
receiving the equivalent injury will be totally equal and therefore we'll never
need all five categories
of payment because they'll all be included within that injury. ולהאי נמי
אית ליה צערא ve-le-hai nami is leh tza'ara and this one, he'll
also have the pain and suffering. That is, both parties will have
experienced more or less equivalent pain and suffering. ומאי קושיא דילמא איכא
איניש דמפנק אית ליה צערא טפי? u-mai kushya dilma ika inish di-mefanak
is leh tza'ara tefai? Or maybe there are people who are more
sensitive and they feel greater pain. ואיכא איניש דלא מפנק לית ליה
צערא ve-ika inish de-lo mefanak leis leh tza'ara and there are people
who are less sensitive and they don't have as much pain and
therefore the pain wouldn't be equal between the two people. מי איריא
Mi irya the fact that suppose two people get into a fight
and they both get beat up, right? They beat each other up.
So you don't just say okay, you know, wipe our hands of
it, it's done, because actually the amount of damage and the amount
of injury caused to each party might not be equivalent. Even though
they both more or less beat each other up what looks like
the same, because they feel the pain differently and because they experience
the injuries differently it might be actually end up being very different.
So you don't just kind of like wipe your hands of it
and move on. דלא נפקא מינה למיתב ליה ההיא דביני ביני. de-lo
nafka minah le-meitav leh ha-hi de-veini beini.
So the point is that that's exactly the argument, which is that
if you're going to give צער, tza'ar, צער tza'ar you can't assess
someone's pain and suffering to always be equivalent one to the next.
There has to be some kind of financial component as well to
equalize it. And once you say that, well then you've said צער
tza'ar is financial. And once you've said צער tza'ar is במקום נזק,
bi-makom nezek, so then the damage itself should also be paid financially
as well. Okay. Okay.
No, I'm sorry. Meaning like if he doesn't feel so much pain,
then you pay money, but if...
Meaning either way, that is the one person... is going to experience
more pain, one person is going to experience less pain. So there
has to be money in between to exchange to equalize those two.
Once you've said there's a financial component of צער. tza'ar. Basically you're
willing to say that צער tza'ar could be financial entirely, there's no
need to cause the person the injury to begin with. And once
we said צער tza'ar is במקום נזק, bimkom nezek, so then the
נזק nezek is also going to be financial. And then you're done.
Then all you've said is there's a financial option and since we
prefer the financial option because it's easier, it's safer, it's better, it's
more
equivalent,
it can be more fairly extended.
Didn't he prove his thing that it's money?
No, we're trying to prove that everything is money.
No, but then we rejected it. Isn't this the objection of the
proof right now? Which proof?
No, the המשלם חצייו ביני ביני. ha-meshalem chatzyo beini beini. No, that
was rejecting his— what? That was supposed to reject his proof that
it meant money. Why? That's what we're trying to do.
We're trying to— why are we trying to reject? Not all of
them are rejected.
The way they're having this here, what does Artscroll say? No, that
this is the rejection of the proof.
Okay, so then fine, so maybe it's the rejection.
Okay.
Okay. I think that's how Rashi says also, איכא דאמרי, ika de'amri,
ומשלם. umeshalem. Okay. Okay, fine. Okay, now understand it.
You find the middle ground.
You find a— right, you was— right, that is it doesn't necessarily
mean it has to be צער, tza'ar, right,
you find the middle ground
in between the two extremes. And you use the amount that will
bring it— you do it in such a way that you cause—
right, you give a monetary compensation to equalize it but that doesn't
mean it's not literal. Right.
Right, doesn't get you off the hook from the actual pain. And
therefore we will go on to Rav Pappa. So, רב פפא משמיה
דרבא אמר. Rav Pappa mishmaya de-Rava amar. אמר קרא, Amar kra, so
what does— he's quoting from Rava, ורפא ירפא. verapo yerape. There's an
obligation for medical, medical expenses. ליתן רפואה במקום נזק. Liten refuah bimkom
nezek. So
the medical expenses are also equivalent kind of payment to נזק. nezek.
Okay. דאי סלקא דעתך ממש, De-ei salka daitach mamash, if you think
it actually refers to blinding someone's eye, והיכי דהאי בעי אסיא האי
נמי בעי אסיא. ve-heichi de-hai ba'ei asya hai nami ba'ei asya. So,
and if you think
at that point that you're going to talk about blinding someone's eye,
then it's not going
to—
meaning,
meaning that by each kind of injury, you
also have to apply medical attention to the guy who you punish.
Exactly, right. And then your eye for taking my eye and then
I gotta pay your medical—
Right, so then there's going to be no need for medical expenses
to be paid at all. And since ורפא ירפא verapo yerape means
you pay for the injury, so but if he's being injured equivalently,
then why do you have to pay back for his medical expense?
Right. סלקא דעתך דהאי סלקא בשר והאי לא סלקא בשר. Salka daitach
de-hai salka basar ve-hai lo salka basar. So or maybe one person
was more seriously injured than the
other. So היכי מהינא תקנתא? heichi mehina takanta? So what's the נפקא
מינה? nafka mina? למיהב ליה האי חצייו ביני ביני? Lemeihav lei hai
chatzyo beini beini? So and again more or less the same type
of rejection we saw by— by צער, tza'ar, that is fine, so
but you find some way in the middle that's going to accommodate
both ways, it's not going to have to be that— it doesn't
mean— it's not a knockout proof that you don't actually cause the
injury. רב אשי אמר. Rav Ashi amar.
No, but— yeah. But if they're going to use this argument, they're
not using it in terms of how to figure out how much
money to give the person.
Correct. Right now it's just is it money at all?
In other words, does this person heal more quickly? Right. Is that
going to come into account in terms of
how much— Well, we're going to have to see, exactly, how much
the medical expenses are going to be is going to be discussed
because exactly that question, whether you go to this doctor or a
different doctor, you go to a specialist who costs more money but
he does a better job healing, like all those kind of questions
are major questions. Yeah.
Plus if it's a מצוה mitzvah to heal someone, but it's— It's
at least permission, right? But
it— it's not obvious that you can get paid for a מצוה,
mitzvah, so this would seem to be the— the source for a
doctor being able to make a living.
Yeah, for sure. That's part of the discussion as well. We know
that obviously— so that
I think actually does come up in some of the discussion of—
of doctoring is how much— how much is it fair for a
doctor to charge and how much— is a doctor allowed to be
making money or is it just payment for, you know, exactly equal
to the services rendered and things like that? Those are very interesting
questions, especially, you know, nowadays people think a lot about medical expenses.
Okay. רב אשי אמר, Rav Ashi amar, אתיא תחת תחת משור. atya
tachat tachat mishor. We learn a גזירה שוה gezeirah shavah from the
word תחת tachat from— from
שור, shor, that is from the damages of— of an ox that
we are already well familiar. Interesting to note, the Vilna Gaon, who
was very good at little גמטריאות gematriaot and things and wordplay, if
you take the letters that are one step down that are תחת
tachat from the word עין, ayin, so after עין ayin comes פ,
pei, after י yod comes כ, kaf, and after נ nun comes
ס. samech. So what does פכס pei-kaf-samech spell? So, תחת תחת משור
*tachat tachat mishor*, so we learn גזירה שוה *Gezeirah Shavah* from the
word תחת *tachat*. כתיב הכא עין תחת עין *Kesiv hacha Ayin tachat
Ayin*. So here it says an eye for
an eye. וכתיב התם שלם ישלם שור shor
תחת השור *Uchsiv hatam shaleim yeshaleim shor tachat hashor*.
And there it says in referring to damages caused by a שור
*shor*, you pay an ox for an ox, but obviously you don't
pay an ox
for an ox, you just pay the money, 'cause we already spent
how many, six chapters talking about that. Okay, so מה להלן ממון,
mamon אף כאן ממון mamon *ma halan mamon, af kan mamon*. Therefore,
since just like by damages by a שור *shor*, you just pay
money, so too by damages between human beings you should also just
pay money. So מאי חזית דילפת תחת תחת משור *mai chazit dyalpat
tachat tachat mishor*? Why should you learn תחת תחת *tachat tachat* the
גזירה שוה *Gezeirah Shavah* using the word תחת *tachat* from the damages
of a שור *shor*, of an ox? נילף תחת תחת מאדם *neilaf
tachat tachat me'adam*. Maybe I should learn תחת תחת *tachat tachat* from
human beings causing damages? דכתיב ונתתה נפש תחת נפש *dichtiv venatata nefesh
tachat nefesh*. By capital crimes. This goes back to a similar kind
of argument we saw yesterday, that is do we compare חובל *chovel*,
that is injuring a person, is it more equivalent to killing a
person or is it more equivalent to injuring an animal or damages
between animals? So let's see here. So נפש תחת נפש *nefesh tachat
nefesh*. מה להלן ממש, אף כאן ממש *ma halan mamash, af kan
mamash*. And there by killing a person, we actually do execute a
person because it's fully ממש *mamash*, that is it's actually what we
require. Okay, so אמרי דיינינן נזיקין מנזיקין ואין דיינינן נזיקין ממיתה *amri
dayninan nezikin minezikin ve'ein dayninan nezikin memitah*. We should learn damages from
other damages and not from capital crimes. So אדרבה דיינינן אדם מאדם
ואין דיינינן אדם מבהמה *aderaba dayninan adam me'adam ve'ein dayninan adam mibeheimah*.
Maybe we should learn human beings from human beings and not from
animals. And that's the קשיא *kashya* on that. So אלא אמר רב
אשי *ela amar Rav Ashi*, so רב אשי *Rav Ashi* now has
the final opinion. So this is where רב אשי *Rav Ashi* himself
first gave one opinion, then it was rejected and רב אשי *Rav
Ashi* can come up with another opinion: ממתחת אשר עינה *mitachat asher
inah*. So that's referring actually to the payment in a case of
rape, I believe, right? ממתחת אשר עינה *mitachat asher inah*,
so ילפת ליה אדם מאדם *yalpat lei adam me'adam*. So there we
learn תחת *tachat* for monetary compensation in a case of human beings.
Okay, ונזיקין מנזיקין *venezikin minezikin*. And it's damages from damages. That is
it's human beings from human beings, is damages from damages, and it's
talking about financial restitution rather than a capital crime. So we see
another case of human beings damaging each other where there's a financial
payment rather than a capital or corporal punishment. So תניא רבי אליעזר
אומר עין תחת עין ממש *tanya Rabbi Eliezer omer Ayin tachat Ayin
mamash*. So, oh, we have the one תנא *Tanna* who seems to
be totally not keeping up with the playbook. רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer*
seems to say עין תחת עין ממש *Ayin tachat Ayin mamash*. עין
תחת עין *Ayin tachat Ayin* actually means poke out somebody's eye. So
ממש סלקא דעתך *mamash salka datach*? Do you really think it means
actually poke out somebody's eye? רבי אליעזר לית ליה כולי הני תנאי
*Rabbi Eliezer leit lei kulei hanei tanna'ei*? Is really רבי אליעזר *Rabbi
Eliezer* disagree with all of these תנאים *Tannaim*? That would undermine our
whole basis of this argument. It would also undermine the statement that
this is דברים המקובלים מפי משה רבינו *devarim hamekubalim mipi Moshe Rabbeinu*,
that it's an undisputed law. Sounds like רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* is
saying that yeah, you do poke out people's eyes. So אמר רבה
לומר שאין שמינו אותו כעבד *amar Rabbah lomar she'ein shaminu oso ke'eved*.
No, it means we don't assess this like the damage caused the
way we do with a slave. That is the way the משנה
*Mishnah* described it. The damage assessment is how much would this person
be sold for as a slave with the injury, how much would
the person be sold before the injury, and then you subtract. שמין
כעבד *shamin ke'eved*. So רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* says no, you assess
the actual eye, how much the eye was worth and not how
much the person would sell for as a slave with and without
the eye. אמר ליה אביי אלא כמאן כבן חורין *amar lei Abayei
ela keman keven chorin*. Rather you assess him like a free person.
בן חורין מי אית ליה דמי *ben chorin mi is lei dmei*?
But is a free person have a monetary value? That is we
only know how much to assess a person's slave value. There's no
value, monetary value associated with being a free person. אלא אמר רב
אשי לומר שאין שמינו אותו בניזק אלא במזיק *ela amar Rav Ashi
lomar she'ein shaminu oso benizak ela bamazik*. No, we don't assess how
much the eye of the injured party was worth, that is how
much damage was caused. We assess how much the person who did
the damage, how much his eye costs and we make him pay
that amount. So it's not like נזיקין *nezikin* where you're paying for
the damage that you caused. It's more like כופר kofer, *kofer*. You
pay the amount of the thing that you now have left over
better than the person who was injured. We saw that by כופר
*kofer* as well. We had the מחלוקת *machlokes* between דמי ניזק nizak.
*dmei nizak* and דמי מזיק mazik *dmei mazik*. Here it sounds like
the דמי מזיק mazik *dmei mazik* side makes it more like a
כופר *kofer* argument and less like a נזק nezek, *nezek* argument. How
do you wouldn't they have a value of a free person when
somebody donates themselves to the amount of? But that's a little bit
different because the only kind of valuation we know even by those
kind of gifts, if you say דמי עלי *dami alai*, if you
say my value goes to the בית המקדש *Beis HaMikdash*, you also
assess the slave value that the person would sell at. I thought
it was a certain, up to 20 and then? That's ערכין *Arachin*.
ערכין *Arachin* is but that's a very precise unique kind of situation.
It's not... Either that that's the person's actual value. That's not what's
meant when they say I'm going to give this and that. No,
those are two different things. They mean the slave value.
So one thing, there are two different things. If you say ערכי
עלי, my ערך, erech, my value, that's a certain category. And if
you say דמיי עלי, damai alai, the my money upon myself, that's
actually a different obligation. That's a more variable thing based on how
much you yourself would be worth as a slave.
We'll get to that in three years.
So today when we don't have slave markets, praise God, at least
in this country,
at least in this country and many other countries, right.
So let's say someone is to physically injure someone else and they
decide to handle to בית דין. Beit Din.
How would—well, we're going to get to that in just a second,
which is that a lot of these issues we don't do anymore
for this reason. So the גמרא Gemara says: So how, I'm sorry,
then how would you make that assessment as כופר, like לפי המזיק?
lefi ha-mazik?
That is, you would see how much does the מזיק sell for
as a slave with his eye and without his eye, right, right.
But you would base it on the מזיק and not on the
ניזק.
Yeah, but you still need
slave—you still need that market value.
Right, right, exactly. ההוא חמרא דקטא ידי דינוקא. Hahu chamra de-kata yadei
de-yinoka.
There was a donkey who bit off or chopped off the hand
of a child. Jeez. Okay. אתא קמיה דרב פפא בר שמואל. Ata
kammai de-Rav Papa bar Shmuel. So he came—so he came to sue
in front of רב פפא בר שמואל. Rav Papa bar Shmuel. אמר
להו זילו שומו ליה ארבעה דברים. Amar le-hu: Zilu shimu lei arba’a
devarim. Go and
collect from him all four things. אמר ליה רבא והא אנן חמשה
תנן?
Amar lei Rava: Ve-ha anan chamsha
tenan?
Don't we say there are five things? That is, if we add
up נזק, nezek. צער, tza’ar, ריפוי, rippui, שבת, shevet, and בושת, boshet,
that's five. Okay. אמר ליה לבר מנזק. Amar lei: Le-bar mi-nezek.
No, I meant four besides נזק. nezek Now what's the problem? It
sounds like we're talking about a donkey. If a donkey causes damage,
it's not החובל, ha-chovel, it's not אדם המזיק. adam ha-mazik. You don't
get all five things, you only collect
damages. So, okay, כמי דאמר—so ka-mida amar אמר ליה אביי והא חמור
חמור הוא?
amar lei Abaye: Ve-ha
chamor, chamor hu? Isn't it a donkey? Okay. וחמור אינו משלם אלא
נזק. Ve-chamor eino meshalem ella nezek. And a donkey only pays for
the נזק nezek and not for the other four. אמר להו זילו
שומו ליה ניזקא. Amar le-hu: Zilu shimu lei nizka. So go collect—assess
how much the damage was. והא כעבדא בעי למישמי. Ve-ha ke-avda ba’ei
le-meshamei. And he said that he has to be judged like a
slave to be assessed. אמר להו זילו שמוהו כעבדא. Amar le-hu: Zilu
shamu-hu ke-avda. So go assess the kid that is a child how
much this child would sell as a slave before and after his
hand was bit off by the donkey. אמר להו אבוה דינוקא לא
בעינא דזילא בי מילתא.
Amar le-hu avuha de-yinoka: Lo ba’ina
de-zilei be-milta. So he doesn't want to because it's very embarrassing, זילא
בי מילתא. zilei be-milta. It's going to be degrading for this child
to be assessed like a slave. אמרו ליה והא קא מיחייבת ליה
לינוקא. Amru lei: Ve-ha ka-michayebat lei le-yinoka. So but—so then what?
So but you're still obligated to pay the damages. But just because
he doesn't want to get assessed? אמר להו לכי גדל מפייסנא ליה
מדידי. Amar le-hu: Le-chi gadil me-fassina lei mi-didei.
So then fine, when he grows up then I'll deal with it
then, more or less. That is, this debt is going to be
hanging over me until the child grows up. Interestingly, of course, what
was—why did they get confused, or why did רב פפא בר שמואל
Rav Papa bar Shmuel was confused about the donkey that he said
you should go collect all four, all five things? Because in Hebrew
and in Aramaic, the word for a donkey and the word for
a donkey driver are very similar. חמור chamor is a donkey, חמר
chammar is the donkey driver. So he thought he said there was
a donkey driver chopped off somebody's hand. Turned out it was the
donkey that bit off somebody's hand. So that's why you have to
pay attention to the details of the case. It's going to change
the way it's assessed. ההוא תורא דאכל ידי דינוקא. Hahu tora de-akhal
yadei de-yinoka. There was an ox that bit off a child's hand.
So אתא לקמיה דרבא. ata lekamei de-Rava. They came before רבא. Rava.
אמר להו זילו שמוהו כעבדא. Amar le-hu: Zilu shamu-hu ke-avda. So go
and assess the child like a slave to find out the value.
אמר ליה והא מר הוא דאמר כל הנישמין כעבד אין גובין אותו
בבבל? Amar lei: Ve-ha mar hu de-amar kol ha-nishamin ke-eved ein govin
oso be-Bavel?
Didn't our master teach us that anyone who's obligated to be assessed
like a slave value we don't judge those sorts of cases in
בבל Bavel because we don't have the proper סמיכה semicha to have
the authority to actually adjudicate those cases? אמר להו לא צריכא דאיתפס.
Amar le-hu: Lo tzricha de-itfas. It must be we're talking about a
case where once the person had already claimed
or already taken the money from the other party, at that point
then you can figure out how much it is and make him
pay back the rest. That is, once you say תפס, tafas, if
he grabbed the money, then you can deal with the case. But
you can't deal with the case sort of from the beginning. That
is because we don't have the authority to judge קנסות kenasot cases,
or to judge even נזק nezek cases. So רבא לטעמיה. Rava le-tamei.
רבא Rava fits his own opinion. דאמר רבא נזקי שור בשור. De-amar
Rava: Nizkei shor be-shor. We're allowed to judge in בבל Bavel and
nowadays as well, שור בשור, shor be-shor, if one animal injured another
animal. ונזקי שור באדם. Ve-nizkei shor be-adam. And if a person—an animal
injured—and if a person injured an animal—no, if an animal injured a
person—גובין אותו בבבל. govin oso be-Bavel. נזקי אדם באדם, Nizkei adam be-adam,
if a person injures another person, ונזקי אדם בשור, ve-nizkei adam be-shor,
or if a person was injured by an animal, אין גובין אותו
בבבל. ein govin oso be-Bavel. Those we cannot collect in בבל. Bavel.
So מאי שנא נזקי אדם באדם ונזקי אדם בשור? mai shna nizkei
adam be-adam ve-nizkei adam be-shor? Why do we say those are different?
דלא אלהים בעינן. De-lo elohim bayinan. That Because in those cases אדם
באדם adam b'adam and אדם בשור, adam b'shor, we require that the
judges be called אלהים. elohim. The word אלהים elohim in פרשת משפטים
parshat mishpatim refers to the judges, it's לשון חול. lashon chol. It
doesn't refer to God and the word אלהים elohim could mean the
judges and the judges have to be in the place of God,
that is they have to have received the full סמיכה semicha going
back to משה רבנו. moshe rabbeinu. But in בבל bavel they didn't
have that סמיכה semicha anymore because you're only allowed to give that
סמיכה semicha in the land of Israel. And once they were outside
the land of Israel, that סמיכה semicha was discontinued. So they couldn't
judge those sort of cases. וליכא? v'leika? וליכא v'leika we don't have
that. נזקי שור בשור ושור באדם, nizkei shor b'shor v'shor b'adam, so
what do we mean? If we say but then what about an
ox that damages another ox or an ox that a person injured
the ox? So נמי אלהים בעינן וליכא. nami elohim bainan v'leika. Don't
we also require אלהים elohim type judges to judge those cases as
well and that's also lacking just the same? אלא מאי שנא שור
בשור ושור באדם דשליחותיהו קעבדינן. ella mai shna shor b'shor v'shor b'adam
d'shlichutaihu ka'avdinan. In the cases of שור בשור, shor b'shor, one animal
kills another injures another animal or or a person injured an animal,
we are their שליחותיהו, shlichutaihu, we are their messengers. That is if
you look in the so the whole principle שליחותיהו קעבדינן, shlichutaihu ka'avdinan,
we are doing their שליחות, shlichut, we are doing their message...
messengering. That is the rabbis in בבל, bavel, perhaps rabbis nowadays as
well, serve as representatives of the High Sanhedrin going back to the
last time when there was a Sanhedrin and in the last place
in the land of Israel. That is in בבל bavel they served
as representatives of the Sanhedrin in ארץ ישראל eretz yisrael and nowadays
we serve as representatives or not we but you know rabbis and
דיינים dayanim serve as as the representatives of the Sanhedrin, the last
Sanhedrin that sat and fixed the law. So בשליחותיהו קעבדינן מידי דהוה
אהודאות והלוואות. b'shlichutaihu ka'avdinan midi d'hava ahodaot v'halvaot. So it has to
be something comparable then to things we are allowed to deal with,
that is הודאות, hodaot, things that people admit to, and הלוואות, halvaot,
loans. אדם באדם ואדם בשור, adam b'adam v'adam b'shor, so maybe you
should say when a person injures another person or an animal injures
a person נמי שליחותיהו קעבדינן? nami shlichutaihu ka'avdinan? So then why wouldn't
you say that that also counts as well we should be their
representatives? מידי דהוה אהודאות והלוואות. midi d'hava ahodaot v'halvaot. No, it should
only be comparable to
to things that people admit to, that is monetary obligations or loans.
אמרי כי קעבדינן שליחותיהו במידי דקים ליה בגוויה. amri ki ka'avdinan shlichutaihu
b'midi d'kim lei b'gavei. We can only serve as
their as their representatives in certain kind of certain kind of cases,
we're gonna have to see what. במידי דלא קים ליה בגוויה לא
עבדינן שליחותיהו. b'midi d'lo kim lei b'gavei lo avdinan shlichutaihu. We can't
serve as their representatives in other sorts of cases. אמרי שור בשור
ושור באדם נמי לא קים ליה בגוויה? amri shor b'shor v'shor b'adam
nami lo kim lei b'gavei? אלא פוק חזי. ella puk chazei. We
should go out and see היכי דמזדבן תורא בשוקא. heichi d'mizdevan tora
b'shuka. So we can see how much a an animal sells for
in the שוק. shuk. אדם באדם ואדם בשור נמי פוק חזי. adam
b'adam v'adam b'shor nami puk chazei. So you should be able to
see how much human beings are sold for in the slave market
to assess that value as well. היכי דמזדבן עבדא בשוקא. heichi d'mizdevan
avda b'shuka. ועוד תשלומי כפל ותשלומי ארבעה וחמישה v'od tashlumei kefel v'tashlumei
arba'ah v'chamishah and then also the קנסות, kenasot, that is you pay
כפל, kefel, you pay ד' וה', daled v'hei, those kind of
fines. דקייצי, d'kaitzei, those are fixed amounts. נמי שליחותיהו, nami shlichutaihu, we
should also serve as their representatives for those as well because those
aren't assessments based on any kind of evaluation, those are fixed on
the price of the damage caused. אמר כי קעבדינן שליחותיהו בממונא בקנסא
לא עבדינן שליחותיהו. amar ki ka'avdinan shlichutaihu b'mamona b'kenasa lo avdinan shlichutaihu.
The only times when we're allowed to serve as as שליחותיהו, shlichutaihu,
the representatives of the
Sanhedrin, בממונא, b'mamona, but not for fines. And here already we see
the distinction between ממון mamon, and קנס. kenas. ממון mamon? is something
much more fluid, much more based on assessments and evaluation, market value,
and קנס kenas is something much more rigid and fixed and precise.
And that precision also requires a higher level authority that the rabbis
in בבל bavel did not have. They don't even feel that their
notion of שליחותיהו קעבדינן, shlichutaihu ka'avdinan, we're doing their we're serving as
their representatives, is enough to get them to cover קנס kenas as
well. Okay. אדם באדם דממונא הוא. adam b'adam d'mamona hu. So then
why still one person punches another person, a person injures another person,
that's ממון, mamon that's monetary
injury, הוא דעביד שליחותיהו. hu d'avid shlichutaihu. כי קעבדינן שליחותיהו במילתא דשכיחא.
ki ka'avdinan shlichutaihu b'milsa d'shchicha. We can only serve as שליחותיהו shlichutaihu
in a case which is
common. אדם באדם דלא שכיחא. adam b'adam d'lo shchicha. But human beings
don't injure each other so often. הלואי, halevai, but that's at least
the suggestion here. It's not so common for one person to injure
another person, לא עבדינן שליחותיהו. lo avdinan shlichutaihu. So we do not
serve as their representatives.
So the בתי דין batei din in בבל bavel didn't hear cases
of חבלה? chabala?
Ah, okay, good question. One second, we're going to get to that
in just a second. I just want to try to finish the
סוגיא sugya but let's pause here for a second at the
end of the it does sound like that.
So if you take a look, it's in the רי"ף rif and
it's also in the טור tur in the first סימן siman in
חושן משפט. choshen mishpat. The רי"ף rif quotes from the גאונים geonim
that the גאונים, geonim,
okay, it's right here.
So the Rif רי"ף Rif quotes that the minhag מנהג minhag in
the two yeshivos ישיבות, yeshivos, that is the two yeshivos ישיבות yeshivos
of Bavel בבל, Bavel, minhag shtei yeshivos she'af al pi she'ein govin
knas beBavel מנהג שתי ישיבות שאף על פי שאין גובין קנס בבבל,
minhag shtei yeshivos she'af al pi she'ein govin knas beBavel, even though
we do not collect knas קנס knas in Bavel בבל, Bavel, that
is the fines, menadin oto ad d'mepayeis leh lebaal dino מנדין אותו
עד דמפייס ליה לבעל דיניה. menadin oto ad d'mepayeis leh lebaal dino.
So we don't collect the knas קנס, knas, but what we do
is we put you in cherem חרם, cherem, we put you in
nidui נידוי, nidui, and until you're willing to pay of your own
accord. That's what the courts did in Bavel בבל Bavel according to
according to the Rif רי"ף. Rif. And the Rif רי"ף Rif and
and the Tur טור Tur quotes that and the Rif רי"ף Rif
seems to really not like it. It doesn't seem to fit the
Gemara גמרא, Gemara, but that's what they did in Bavel בבל. Bavel.
That's what they did in the Geonic period in Bavel בבל. Bavel.
Yes.
The Rif רי"ף Rif lived in North Africa.
The Rif רי"ף Rif lived in North Africa and so did the
Tur טור Tur but Bavel בבל. Bavel. But he was part of
he probably either he studied with teachers who had studied in Bavel
בבל Bavel or he received the tradition there was throughout the Muslim
caliphate.
The tradition was from Bavel בבל. Bavel.
Right. And actually there was an extensive.
Well the Baghdad.
Well the trade routes and the letters and things would be sent
through the the Muslim world. There was actually very good communication.
They were under the same rule at that point.
Right. Right. So I mean again the Rif רי"ף Rif was maybe
a few hundred years later, but the tradition he received and the
teachers he studied with went back through. Now Ashkenaz אשכנז Ashkenaz also
had a certain amount of contact with the Geonim גאונים, Geonim, but
significantly less. And that's obviously many of the Ashkenazic departures from the
Geonic tradition are because it
was more from Eretz Yisrael ארץ ישראל.
Eretz Yisrael. Perhaps more from Eretz Yisrael ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and
Italy and Greece and things like that. It becomes complicated when you
try to pin some of that stuff down. Okay, so we're in
the middle of the question of shlichusaihu ka avdina שליחותייהו קא עבדינן.
shlichusaihu ka avdina. Shmuel wanted to share one point from Tosfos תוספות
Tosfos in Yevamos יבמות Yevamos before we continue with the Gemara גמרא
Gemara just because I think it's important. Tosfos תוספות Tosfos in Yevamos
יבמות Yevamos on mem zayin amud alef מ"ז עמוד א' mem zayin
amud alef right at the top is discussing the question of conversion.
Conversion nowadays well doesn't conversion also require a beis din בית דין
beis din who serve as elohim אלוהים? elohim? It has to be
a real beis din בית דין beis din with smicha סמיכה. smicha.
So that's one suggestion at least. And the suggestion is yeah well
we could say shlichusaihu ka avdina שליחותייהו קא עבדינן shlichusaihu ka avdina
to accept to accept converts but then you have the question wait
a second, to be able to serve as shlichusaihu שליחותייהו shlichusaihu you
have to have chesron kis חסרון כיס, chesron kis, there's a loss
of of financial loss and it has to be something that's shachiach
שכיח, shachiach, that's common. So we could understand conversion is something that's
considered common, shachiach שכיח, shachiach, but where's the monetary loss? Where's the
chesron kis חסרון כיס? chesron kis? And Tosfos תוספות Tosfos basically concludes
just like we say kmo shechashu lineilas deles bifnei lavin כמו שחשו
לנעילת דלת בפני לווין, kmo shechashu lineilas deles bifnei lavin, just like
we're concerned about if the court won't be able to judge this
kind of case then people will default on their loans and there
will be no more people willing to make loans and then the
lenders will lose out because the borrowers will lose out because no
one will lend to them because they won't be able to go
to court, so too Tosfos תוספות Tosfos says chashu nami lineilas deles
bifnei gerim חשו נמי לנעילת דלת בפני גרים. chashu nami lineilas deles
bifnei gerim. We're concerned as well the same kind of motivation even
if it's not actually a financial concern, but to close off the
avenues to conversion into Judaism would also be a similar kind of
restriction. Being too strict about that would actually prevent very many people
who would be willing and interested in joining the Jewish people and
being good upstanding gerim גרים gerim
would be closed off from that access. And therefore we could say
shlichusaihu ka avdina שליחותייהו קא עבדינן, shlichusaihu ka avdina, we serve as
representatives of the beis din בית דין beis din of the Sanhedrin
סנהדרין Sanhedrin even to accept converts as well. So that's Tosfos תוספות
Tosfos on mem zayin amud alef מ"ז עמוד א' mem zayin amud
alef in Yevamos יבמות. Yevamos. It's the opposite of trying to dissuade.
In other words at a certain point it's very positive. Right. It's
very powerful. Those sugyos סוגיות sugyos and we will get to them
in what five years from now and again we'll be able to
see them again. Very powerful sugya סוגיא sugya about about conversion. Okay,
so the Gemara גמרא Gemara continues. Hari boshes upgam d'shachiach הרי בושת
ופגם דשכיח. hari boshes upgam d'shachiach. So what about boshes בושת, boshes,
embarrassment and pgam פגם, pgam, devaluation. That is something similar to the
idea of where pgam פגם pgam usually is in the case of
ones u'mepateh אונס ומפתה, ones u'mepateh, those are rape cases and things
like that where the woman's sense of how much she'll be able
to receive in terms of the marriage agreement, that amount that now
that she has been raped is going to create a certain amount
of devaluation in that sense. So that's the pgam פגם, pgam, also
carries with it obviously the boshes בושת, boshes, the embarrassment of of
such a crime as well. So those those situations, so shlichusaihu b'boshes
u'pgam d'shachiach שליחותייהו בבושת ופגם דשכיח. shlichusaihu b'boshes u'pgam d'shachiach. Those are
common again. How they assess what's common and what's not. A person
punching another person is considered not so common, but rape was considered
much more common. I'm not really sure how they determine what's shachiach
שכיח shachiach or not or things have changed significantly. But nonetheless so
it says boshes upgam d'shachiach naavid shlichusaihu בושת ופגם דשכיח נעביד שליחותייהו.
boshes upgam d'shachiach naavid shlichusaihu. So maybe we should serve as their
representatives for those as well even though they're based on knas קנס
knas because there's a knas קנס knas in the case of ones
u'mepateh אונס ומפתה. ones u'mepateh. Amri hachi nami אמרי הכי נמי. amri
hachi nami. So in these cases also. Deha Rav Papa agabei arba
me'ah zuzei l'boshes דהא רב פפא אגבי ארבע מאה זוזי לבושת. deha
Rav Papa agabei arba me'ah zuzei l'boshes. So so Rav Papa רב
פפא Rav Papa collected 400 zuz זוז zuz for boshes בושת boshes
for an embarrassment case. V'ha l'ita והא ליתא. v'ha l'ita. והא ליתיה
דרב פפה דשלח ליה רב חסדא לרב נחמן דשלח ליה חסדא חסדא
קנסא קא מגבית בבבל
ve-ha le-iteih de-Rav Pappa
de-shalach lei Rav Chisda le-Rav Nachman de-shalach lei Chisda Chisda knasa ka
magbeita be-Vavel so he sent him חסדא חסדא Chisda Chisda are you
really collecting קנס knas fines in בבל? Bavel? אלא כי עבדינן שליחותייהו
במידי דשכיחא Ella ki advinan shelichutaihu be-mildi de-shachicha it must be common
ואית ביה חסרון כיס ve-it beih chesron kis and it has a
financial loss. What's the difference between a קנס knas and ממון? mamon
ממון mamon, is something I actually deserve. ממון mamon is something someone
is trying to take my money away and I'm trying to get
it back. That's ממון, mamon that's חסרון כיס. chesron kis. A קנס
knas is is a punishment or as a some kind of additional
component. The Torah said part of the punishment for doing this is
that you have to pay this amount of money but it's not
מגיע לי, magi'a li, it's not I don't deserve it in any
way. And that's the difference between ממון mamon and קנס. knas. קנס
knas fundamentally is something the בית דין Beit Din imposes. It's not
something that the litigant deserves in any sense. So במידי דשכיחא ולית
ביה חסרון כיס
be-mildi de-shachicha ve-leit beih
chesron kis things which are common even though they lack חסרון כיס
chesron kis לא עבדינן שליחותייהו lo advinan shelichutaihu we could not. אי
נמי מידי דלא שכיחא i nami mildi de-lo shachicha if it's not
common ואית ביה חסרון כיס ve-it beih chesron kis and even if
it has חסרון כיס chesron kis that is you're losing out on
money but it's not so common לא עבדינן שליחותייהו lo advinan shelichutaihu
we cannot serve as their representatives. הלכך אדם באדם hilkach adam be-adam
therefore one person injuring another person אף על גב דאית ביה חסרון
כיס af al gav de-it beih chesron kis even though
there is a financial loss, that is there's נזק and בושת boshet
and צער tza'ar and ריפוי, rippui, כיון דלא שכיחא keivan de-lo shachicha
since it's not so common לא עבדינן שליחותייהו.
lo advinan shelichutaihu.
In that case we cannot serve as their representatives
that
is we're not allowed to collect in those
cases. So בושת, boshet, what about בושת boshet embarrassment? אף על גב
דשכיחא af al gav de-shachicha it's very common, כיון דלית ביה חסרון
כיס keivan de-leit beih chesron kis since there's no real sense of
חסרון כיס, chesron kis, that is the amount of money you pay
for בושת boshet is not really that you lost money, it's that
someone is paying you back for something they did to you. You
were embarrassed by the situation. So it's not that someone took your
money away and now they're giving it back, they made fun of
you and they owe you compensation for that. So that's not considered
חסרון כיס, chesron kis, so לא עבדינן שליחותייהו. lo advinan shelichutaihu. So
in בושת boshet we also shouldn't make a we shouldn't be considered
their representative. דהשור בשור de-ha-shor be-shor what about if one animal injures
another? גובים בבבל. govin be-Vavel. We can serve as representatives in בבל.
Bavel. והאמר רבא שור שהזיק אין גובים אותו בבבל ve-ha amar Rava
shor she-hizik ein govin oto be-Vavel didn't רבא Rava say if an
ox caused damage we do not collect on that in בבל? Bavel?
דהזיק מאן אילימא דהזיק אדם de-hizik man i-leima de-hizik adam no, what
he meant is when it injures a person then you cannot collect
for it in בבל. Bavel. מאי איריא שור דהזיק אדם אפילו אדם
דהזיק אדם נמי אין גובים אותו בבבל mai irya shor de-hizik adam
afilu adam de-hizik adam nami ein govin oto be-Vavel so then we
should say even if a person injures another person we shouldn't be
able to collect in בבל Bavel at all, not just not the
בושת boshet but not anything at all. אלא פשיטא דהזיק שור ella
peshita de-hizik shor it must be that רבא Rava was talking about
when an ox injured another ox וקתני אין גובים אותו בבבל. ve-katani
ein govin oto be-Vavel. He said that you cannot collect in בבל.
Bavel. אמרי התם בתם amri hatam be-tam he must be talking about
a שור תם shor tam that is שור תם shor tam חצי
נזק, chatzi nezek, חצי נזק chatzi nezek we saw at least according
to some opinions is considered a קנס. knas. So we've gone back
to the whole point that a קנס knas for שור תם shor
tam you wouldn't collect in בבל. Bavel. הכא במועד hacha be-muad but
a case of מועד muad you would collect because מועד muad is
basically paying back the full price of the damages rather than the
קנס. knas. והאמר רבא אין מועד בבבל ve-ha amar Rava ein muad
be-Vavel there's no, sorry, the opposite. I said the opposite. שור תם
shor tam fine. So he has to be saying that שור תם
shor tam חצי נזק chatzi nezek of שור תם shor tam is
more like ממון and paying back in a case of שור מועד
shor muad once it's gotten to the point of שור מועד shor
muad then you can't collect on it in בבל. Bavel. אמרי דאיעד
התם ואייתוהו להכא amri de-iyad hatam ve-aituha le-hacha so how could they
have made a שור שור מועד shor shor muad in בבל? Bavel?
That is the whole point is if you can't judge שור תם
shor tam case in בבל Bavel how could you ever get to
the point where it's מועד? muad? It has to have been תם
tam three times before it becomes מועד. muad. So number one, אמרי
דאיעד התם ואייתוהו להכא amri de-iyad hatam ve-aituha le-hacha maybe it became
מועד muad in ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael where they have real judges
and then the cow came to בבל, Bavel, possibility number one. והא
מידי דלא שכיחא היא ve-ha mildi de-lo shachicha hi but that's not
very common, an ox is never going to travel from ארץ ישראל
Eretz Yisrael to בבל Bavel meaning people rarely made that journey קל
וחומר kal va-chomer that an animal would never would never be schlepped
across. ומידי דלא שכיחא הא אמרת דלא עבדינן שליחותייהו u-mildi de-lo shachicha
ha amrat de-lo advinan shelichutaihu so then we can't serve as representatives
for something that's not so common. דאתו רבנן דהתם ויאעדוה הכא de-atu
rabbanan de-hatam ve-iyaduha hacha so maybe the Rabbis from Israel came to
בבל Bavel and since they have סמיכה semicha they were able to
make a שור מועד shor muad in בבל Bavel using their good
סמיכה. semicha. סוף סוף מידי דלא שכיחא היא sof sof mildi de-lo
shachicha hi but that's also not common. ואת אמרת מידי דלא שכיחא
לא עבדינן שליחותייהו ve-at amrat mildi de-lo shachicha lo advinan shelichutaihu and
therefore we can't judge this case anyway. אלא כי אמר רבא בשן
ורגל דמועדים מתחילתן נינהו ella ki amar Rava be-shen va-regel de-muadim mi-tchillatan
ninhu no, it must be what רבא Rava was talking about that
we don't judge שור case in בבל Bavel means a case which
could happen in בבל Bavel that is שן ורגל. shen va-regel. שן
ורגל shen va-regel are מועדים מתחילתן, muadim mi-tchillatan, they're מועד muad immediately
as we already learned. It's only קרן keren that has the distinction
between תם tam and מועד. muad. Therefore שן ורגל shen va-regel would
be considered מועדים מתחילתן, muadim mi-tchillatan, מועד muad from the beginning to
pay full damage which is ממון and you could do it in
בבל, Bavel, nonetheless רבא Rava says no no no we don't do
it in בבל. Bavel. And that's where we'll leave off for today.
Ian, I have a question. Sure, one second. Is the authority of
the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa greater than the authority of the נשיא?
Nasi? In some ways, yes, because the ריש גלותא Reish Galusa has
the power of the monarchy, of מלכות, malchus, whereas the נשיא Nasi
is the head of the סנהדרין. Sanhedrin. We'll speak more about this
tomorrow. All right, have a good day. Thank you. You're welcome.